Let's get started.
Today we're going to be
talking about exploration.
We're going to be starting
by talking about exploration
in standard reinforcement
learning settings,
actually, primarily,
in bandit settings,
and then how that might
translate to robotics
and large language models.
And then we're actually
going to revisit
some of the meta-learning
topics that we talked about
on Wednesday and revisit how
we might effectively learn how
to explore in meta-RL settings.
So what is the
exploration problem?
If we apply reinforcement
learning to some problems,
we're able to solve
them quite well.
So for example, if we try to
train a reinforcement learning
agent to play Breakout,
where the reward is
the score of the game, you get a
pretty performant player that's
able to get a high score.
But if you instead try to train
a reinforcement learning agent
to play a game like this
one on the right, which
is called Montezuma's
Revenge, it's
really, really hard for
reinforcement learning systems
to play.
Now, why is there
this difference?
So in the second game, you can
get a reward if you get a key.
Kind of intuitively, if
you're getting a key,
that's useful for
being able to progress.
Opening a door is also useful.
And there's this skull
that's rolling around.
And intuitively,
we as humans know
that that's probably something
you might want to avoid.
Likewise, falling off of
a ledge might be something
that you'd avoid.
But these are things that the
agent doesn't know itself.
And in general, kind
of completing the game,
these are very sparse,
discrete events.
And completing the game
only weakly correlates
relates with those
rewarding events.
And so actually, each of those
individual rewarding events
are also kind of
few and far between.
So for example,
at the beginning,
the agent isn't getting
any reward at all
and it has to figure out
how to even get to the key
in the first place,
which requires quite
a long sequence of events.
Now, as humans, we
kind of know what
to do because we
understand what each
of these sprites
in the game mean.
But the algorithm really
doesn't know that.
So if we instead try
to imagine ourselves
as reinforcement
learning algorithms,
let's think through
that a little bit.
And we can think through
that with a game called Mao.
It's like half a game,
half a joke in some ways.
You aren't told the rules
of the game in advance.
And if you break a rule,
then you get a penalty.
And you don't actually know.
You get a penalty, but you don't
actually know what the rule is,
and you have to discover the
rules through trial and error.
And when you get a penalty,
it's not always clear
why you got a penalty.
The rules don't actually
necessarily make sense to you.
And tasks like
Montezuma's Revenge
are difficult because
reinforcement learning methods,
they don't know about the rules.
They know very little
about what's good
and what's bad, what they
can do, what they can't do.
And when tasks become
longer and longer,
this also makes the problem
even more difficult,
because you have to figure
out an even longer sequence
of actions that might
lead to getting reward
versus getting a penalty.
And so if you think about what
the reinforcement learning
agent has to do,
reinforcement learning agents
are kind of analogous to
imagining if your goal in life
was to win 50 games of Mao,
and you also didn't even
know this in advance.
You only kind of learned this
from actually getting rewards,
from winning games and getting
penalties from losing games.
So that's what the
reinforcement learning system--
that's the difficulty that
these algorithms are faced with.
It's really, really
hard, especially
in sparse-reward scenarios.
Now, if we were to think about
this exploration problem,
there's a couple different
ways of looking at it.
One way of looking at it is,
we want to discover high reward
strategies.
We want to basically seek out
rewards and find sequences
of actions that, individually,
those actions may not
be rewarding, but when
we seek them together,
we're able to find rewards.
And another way to view
the exploration problem
is deciding whether to
attempt a new behavior,
or continuing to do the best
thing that it knows so far.
You're basically deciding,
should I try something new,
or should I do something that
has been good in the past?
These are actually part
of a single problem,
where you need to--
there's this
exploitation problem,
which is doing what you know
will yield the highest reward,
doing the things that
you've seen before that have
high reward, acting
according to your Q function,
for example, and this
exploration problem,
which is doing things that you
haven't done before in hopes
of getting higher reward.
And so that's how we can
think about this reinforcement
learning problem, where we
need to balance these two
objectives if our
goal is to maximize
a sum of rewards over time.
As some examples, if
you are in a new city,
you move somewhere
new, exploration
would be trying new restaurants.
Exploitation would be going
to your favorite restaurant
or restaurant that
you like the best.
One actually very common use
of reinforcement learning
is figuring out which
ads to place and where.
And exploitation would
be taking the ad that
has been the most successful and
showing that one to the user.
An exploration would
be instead, trying
to pick a different
advertisement at random,
and instead showing that
advertisement to the user.
Or as a kind of a final
example, in oil drilling,
you don't know where
you're going to find--
where you're going to find oil.
And so exploitation would
be taking the best location
that you've found before
that has yielded oil,
versus exploration would be
drilling at a new location.
So exploration is quite hard.
And if we want to design an
algorithm for exploration,
we might think about what is
the best strategy for exploring
and the best way to trade
off between exploration
and exploitation.
And we also need to
think about, what
does optimality of
exploration even mean?
There's a range of
reinforcement learning problems,
ranging from more
simple problems
where you can actually
analyze whether or not
the strategy is optimal or not,
to more complicated problems
where it's intractable to
analyze whether or it's optimal,
and also intractable
to develop algorithms
that are able to do a
good job at exploration.
On the simple side, you start
with multi-armed bandits,
the kind of one-step RL problems
that don't have any state.
And then if you want to
make that more complicated,
you add context.
You add some sort of features
for each POS for the state
that you're in.
You could then move to
small MDPs, to larger MDPs.
And a lot of the
kind of problems
that we've been talking
about in this course
are large MDPs without
any known structure,
and those are the ones that are
like the hardest for getting
good exploration strategy,
and also, theoretically,
thinking about exploration.
So before we talk
about exploration
in the large problems,
let's talk a little bit
about bandits for a minute,
because they provide a nice way
to think about exploration.
And they're actually
used in practice
for a variety of problems.
And specifically, the way
that we can think about--
what is a bandit?
It's not the kind of someone
that runs around and maybe tries
to steal stuff or something.
It's a formulation of
reinforcement learning,
where the horizon is just one
time step for a single episode.
There is no state.
And unlike everything we've
talked about in MDP so far,
your reward is
actually stochastic.
And so if you go back
to the examples before,
you could think
about the problem
as selecting a restaurant
as a bandit problem where
you could, for example, select
to go to one restaurant.
You could select to go to
a different restaurant.
a different restaurant,
and so forth.
And depending on your
experience in previous episodes
of selecting restaurants,
you could inform your choice
about whether you want to pick
a new restaurant where you know
nothing about the reward,
or go to a restaurant
that you've received high
reward for it in the future.
And the reward is
stochastic in the sense
that your experience
at that restaurant
may not be the same
every single time.
And so yeah, this is what a
bandit problem looks like.
Now, if we want to think
about how good is exploration
and how good is
our reinforcement
learning algorithm,
we want to think
about how much reward we're
getting relative to if we
were acting optimally.
And so far, we've been
thinking about sums of rewards,
oftentime averaged
over episodes.
In bandit problems,
you actually are
often thinking about, actually,
the entire reinforcement
learning process, and the
optimality of the reinforcement
optimality of exploration
followed by exploitation.
And so say that you have taken
capital T episodes so far.
Then the best you
could have done
is going to be something like
the expected reward of taking
the optimal action times T. And
this is actually in some ways
an oracle, because when you
haven't taken any episodes
at the beginning,
then you are forced
to take a random action
because you don't know anything
about the MDP so far.
And so this is kind
of, in retrospect,
what is the best thing
you could have done.
And this is a upper bound
on the sum of rewards
that you could be
getting after T episodes.
And then if we want to think
about how well we've been doing,
we can think about this
subtracted by the sum of rewards
that we actually observed from
the actions that we've taken.
And so that would be
something like a sum from T
equals 1 to T of the
action-- the actual action
that we decided to take in
each particular episode.
And the gap between these
two is going to be measuring,
basically, a form
of optimality gap.
And this expression is
something that's called regret.
And it's measuring,
basically, how much
do we regret taking the
action that we did compared
to taking the optimal action.
Now, if you were to think
about regret over time,
so here, actually, time
is indexing over episodes
because each episode is
just a single time step.
So if we think
about as a function
of the number of
episodes, the regret
after taking those
number of episodes.
If you were acting
optimally, what sort of curve
would you get on this plot?
Yeah, so I see mostly
going straight.
So if you're acting
optimally, this will be zero,
and it will be zero even as you
have more and more episodes.
It'll be zero in expectation.
There might be some randomness.
And so you would get a
curve that looks like this.
And so this is sort of optimal.
Now, in practice,
actually achieving
this is not really possible
because at the first time step,
like I mentioned, you have
to take a random action.
Now, does anyone have thoughts
on what this curve would
look like if you were just
taking an episode at random.
Yeah, it'll keep increasing.
Yeah.
So if you're taking
an episode at random,
there will now be a
gap between these,
and you would be
getting a higher reward
from taking the optimal
action compared to taking
that action at random.
And if, for example, you
were always picking A1,
and A1 is not the best action,
then after one episode,
you would expect to have
some kind of non-zero regret.
So you would have a curve
that looks like this.
And then if you took A1
again the next episode,
then you would then
incur the same difference
in optimal rewards versus
the rewards that you took.
And so then this would
increase, and you would actually
get something that looks linear.
And that means that,
basically, every time you--
basically, at every
time step, there's
a fixed difference between the
optimal reward and the reward
that you took.
And so whenever you get a linear
regret increasing linearly,
that means that your algorithm
is not actually improving.
It's not actually
using the exploration
to get better rewards.
If instead you were--
the blue markers never worked
that well, but we can see.
If instead you were actually
having an algorithm that
is a bit smarter, then you would
expect to have sublinear regret.
And so you'd expect actually
not just linearly increase
your regret over
time, but actually
have this curve look
something like this,
where it starts looking
something more like linear.
And then eventually, if you
then get to the optimal behavior
after exploring,
then it flattens out
to something like this.
And you could imagine that
this portion is like you're now
in the exploitation phase.
And the phase
before that is when
you're exploring and gathering
information about the problem.
The question is, to
make these curves,
are we running the learning
process a lot of different times
and then averaging?
So for these curves,
this is actually--
each of these curves is just one
reinforcement learning process.
And I guess they're
very smooth here,
and in practice, they'll
be a little bit noisier.
The optimal, I guess, this
is kind of an expectation.
And so this is
going to be smooth.
But you might have something
where, for example, in reality,
maybe you got unlucky
one time step.
And this went up
because you got unlucky.
Maybe at the next time step, you
still took the optimal action
but got lucky.
And so this will actually have
some noise in it in practice.
Yeah, so the question is,
we have an expectation
on the first part.
We don't have an
expectation here.
Why is that?
This is basically some measure
of the optimal expected
reward after T time steps.
This is actually just the
actual reward that you observed.
You could also have an
expectation over this,
over reinforcement
learning runs.
And that would then give you--
as an example here, if you run
this algorithm multiple times,
these regret curves
will actually
look a little bit
different depending
on how unlucky you get.
And then if you
were to then measure
this in terms of
expectations, then that
would be averaging
over different runs
of the reinforcement
learning algorithm.
Yeah, so the question is, if
we're taking random actions,
why is it linear, and why is it
increasing by a fixed amount?
So this will be noisy if you
are taking random actions.
I don't know how to say that.
So yeah, it will be noisy.
If you run it multiple times in
expectation, it will be linear.
And if you have a
deterministic MDP
and you always select
action 1 through a very not
smart strategy, and the rewards
are a bit more deterministic,
then you might actually get
a curve that looks like this.
So the question is, if
we're always taking A1,
then how do we actually know
how to measure this formula?
This is not actually
a formula that--
sorry.
To back up a little bit,
this is actually not--
this is what we're aiming to--
we're aiming to minimize regret.
And we're aiming
to get something
that is able to flatten out.
But this is more of an object
that's used for analysis
and not our
optimization objective,
because we actually
can't measure this
without knowledge of
the bandit problem,
or knowledge of the MDP.
If you introduce an
expectation here,
then you would expect
it to be monotonic.
If not, then because the
reward is stochastic,
you could have
scenarios where you
say that the best action
is A5, and the probability
of getting good reward is--
I don't know-- 90% of the
time, and 10% of the time,
you get a bad reward.
Then you're going to see,
when you get a good reward,
it will actually relative to the
expert which is averaging over
that, it will go down.
But if you write this
as an expectation
for the reinforcement
learning algorithm,
it would be monotonic.
Cool.
So this is the regret
formula, regret
after doing reinforcement
learning for T episodes.
Expected reward of
the best action,
basically, the best we can
hope for in expectation,
if we had knowledge
of what the bandit is.
And then this is the
reward of the action
that's actually taken.
There's a variety of simple
strategies for exploration,
and including some that you
can show that are optimal.
And you can often
analyze algorithms
and provide theoretical
guarantees on regret.
And then also,
even the algorithms
that you can theoretically
make some guarantees
about in practice,
performance can vary.
And so to get a little bit
more intuition-- actually, no.
Before we do that-- we're going
to play a game in a minute,
but before we do
that, let's talk
about different strategies
for exploration,
so specifically in
bandits, so not in MDPs.
So one approach is when you're
selecting different restaurants,
for example, if you haven't
explored a restaurant,
then you could choose
to be optimistic
about that restaurant.
And that will incentivize you
to explore new restaurants,
rather than always being greedy
with respect to restaurants
you've tried before.
And so the way
this could work is
you could track
the average reward
that you have received in the
past for each of the actions.
And then if you
were to exploit, you
would just take
the action that has
the maximum average
reward for the things
that you've seen so far.
But instead, if we want to
actually encourage the algorithm
to visit new things,
then we could--
we still want to
visit actions that we
think have high average
rewards, so that if we
go to a restaurant
that's really bad,
we maybe don't go to it again.
But we're going to add a term
that is some kind of variance
of our reward estimate.
This is basically like,
if this variance is high,
that means that we're
uncertain about the reward
for that action.
And if we're
uncertain, then we're
going to basically give
this sort of bonus,
this sort of reward
bonus, on top
of our estimate of
the average reward
to encourage our
algorithm to explore
things that are uncertain, or
things that have high variance.
And so the intuition
here is that we're
assuming that unknown things
are going to be good until we
actually then observe them.
And if we then observe them
and they're really bad,
then we'll act accordingly.
In the future, the
variance will go down,
and the reward
estimate will go down.
And this is a way to balance
exploration and exploitation.
Yeah, so the question is, how
would you choose in this case
an action that you
haven't seen before?
So if you haven't
seen an action before,
then your variance estimate
will be something like infinite,
for example.
And then this will encourage
it to explore, basically,
all of the actions that
it hasn't explored first
at least once.
And then from
there, your variance
will go-- your variance
estimate or your uncertainty
about an action will
go down over time.
And yeah, so this is basically,
if you haven't done anything
before, it will incentivize
it to visit that first.
Cool.
So this is a popular algorithm.
You can actually derive
guarantees for it.
It's called upper confidence
bound, or one version of it
is called upper
confidence bound.
There's another
approach that you
can also take that is actually
harder to show guarantees for,
but can work pretty
well in practice.
And we actually saw something
like this in the last lecture.
And essentially, what
you're trying to do
is you're trying to estimate
the probability of getting
good rewards from each of
the arms of the bandit.
And so the way
this would work is
you assume that there's some
sort of distribution of rewards
for each of the actions.
And this defines a
partially observed MDP
where you don't know the
parameters of the reward
function.
You don't know if
you're going to get
a good reward or bad reward.
And so you'll then actually
try to model and form
an estimate of the
likelihood of getting rewards
by trying to model these
parameters in your uncertainty
over it.
So you'll form an
estimate with any data
that you've seen so far.
Then you'll actually
sample an MDP
from your model of
possible MDPs of the world,
and then you'll take
the optimal action,
assuming that your
sample was correct,
and then repeat that process
to update your beliefs again,
and then sample a new MDP,
and repeat the process.
And we'll walk
through an example.
But the intuition here is
that you can iteratively
improve your model of the
bandit and act according
to one of the models
that is covered
by one of the potential
sets of probabilities that's
modeled by your MDP model.
One last note,
these are actually
methods that are
widely used and studied
in industry for recommenders
and ad placement.
Everything we've been
talking about so far
is for these sorts of
small bandit problems,
but they are actually
quite relevant for a number
of practical problems, even when
you don't have longer episodes
or episodes with state.
And now, let's
play a little game
to get some intuition
for how this works.
So here is a little simulation.
Say that you are hired as
the head of drug development
at a prestigious
research hospital.
Things are going well, and now
there's some sort of plague,
and you need to
figure out what drugs
are going to be effective
for addressing the plague.
And you want to save
people's lives by giving them
the drug that's most effective.
Now, you can recognize this as a
bandit problem, where each drug,
you don't know how
capable it's going to be.
And we can say that
maybe there is--
maybe there's somewhere
around 5,000 patients,
and there's maybe around
10 different drugs that
you're considering.
And your goal is to try
to understand-- well, try
to save lives, try to save
as many lives as possible,
but also balancing saving lives
right now versus saving lives
in the future as you
learn information
about each of the drugs.
Cool.
So let's play.
Who wants to suggest a drug?
Drug one.
OK.
So we see that we
prescribe drug one.
The patient lived,
so that's good.
Who wants to pick a drug?
Yeah?
Four.
OK.
We also see the patient lived.
This is good, on a good track.
Yeah.
10.
10?
Died.
OK.
Yeah?
Seven.
Seven?
Lived.
OK.
So one, four and seven
are looking better than 10
right now.
Someone else?
Yeah?
Six?
Still exploring.
Patient died.
Five?
Died.
OK, not so good.
Who else?
Yeah.
Seven again.
Seven.
OK, maybe we want
to start exploiting.
Patient lived again, so
that seems pretty good.
Who wants to suggest?
Yeah.
Two.
Patient died.
Not so good.
Yeah.
Seven.
OK.
Patient lived again.
Pretty good.
What do we want to do next?
Seven?
OK, do we want to
keep doing seven?
Patient died.
Yeah?
Eight?
Patient died.
Seven?
Patient lived.
All right, should we just keep
on going seven at this point?
Are we happy with seven?
Try nine.
Patient lived.
Try one.
Patient died.
Four, patient lived.
Four again.
Patient died.
Nine, patient lived.
Three, patient died.
OK, we like nine?
Cool.
Maybe let's keep on doing nine.
Patient is living a lot.
Great.
We have one patient died.
So let's say that we kept on
going with nine for a while.
And then we can plot--
actually, well, with 5,000,
which I could just say keep
on doing nine.
Maybe we'll stop there and we
can actually plot the regret.
So this was the true
efficacy of the drugs,
and we can see that nine
actually was the best one,
so we actually found the
best one, which is good.
Seven was also pretty good.
And then we could
also plot the number
of lives that are saved
by different algorithms.
And so higher here is better.
And we see that the
posterior sampling approach--
And in this case, what posterior
sampling would be doing
is modeling the probability
of the efficacy of each drug.
And then based on
this estimate of that,
picking something that's better.
And we can see that how well
we did right here is in purple.
It's a little bit hard
to tell just because it's
a little small, but we can
see that, generally, it
looks like we're doing pretty
well relative to the algorithms.
And then you can also
plot regret over time.
And actually, here we can see
that we're actually doing better
than all the algorithms.
So you guys are pretty good.
Nice.
Maybe there's some
luck involved there,
so this is just a single run.
And what these different
algorithms are is you see greedy
is showing green.
Greedy is just picking the
best thing you've seen so far.
And over time, especially
with more and more trials
that you might be running,
like more and more
patients, more and
more ad placements,
whatever, it's
getting a lot worse.
In this case, we saw that
posterior sampling, yellow,
is by far the best algorithm.
And then the other algorithms,
red is showing epsilon greedy.
Blue is showing UCB, so
that's the first algorithm
we talked about with
being optimistic
about uncertain actions.
So this is basically
showing the trade-off
between different algorithms.
One other thing to note
that epsilon greedy,
it's a bit more
greedy, and so we
see that with-- when
you have fewer patients,
it actually is doing
better than UCB.
But then in the long
run, UCB is doing
better because it's actually
optimizing a bit more
for making sure that you're
exploring more actions.
And so in the long run,
it's able to take more
optimal actions in the future.
Is there a
mathematical reason why
posterior sampling does better
than UCB and epsilon greedy?
Yeah.
So I don't want to go
too much into the math.
And actually, posterior
sampling, for this MDP,
you probably could analyze it.
But in general, it
can be hard to derive
general theoretical
guarantees for it.
With regard to epsilon
greedy, I guess some of it
comes down to that
value of epsilon,
and then tuning it to be--
and generally, with
epsilon greedy,
you often choose epsilon to be
smaller and smaller over time.
And that hyperparameter would
probably drastically impact
performance, because at
this point in training,
if epsilon is constant, you're
going to be keeping on--
you're going to be
still occasionally
taking random drugs.
And at that point, you already
know a lot about the drug,
and prescribing a random
drug is a very poor choice.
Cool.
So also, if you want
to play more, you can--
I'll put the website
in the slides.
So that's exploration
in bandits.
Now, what does this look like
for robotics, language models
and larger MDPs?
Different people have
different opinions on this.
I have a somewhat
pessimistic opinion on it.
And in particular,
there's actually
a lot of research that try to
translate these ideas to larger
MDPs.
For example, you
can try to formulate
some estimate of whether
you've taken an action or not,
and give reward
bonuses for novelty,
for visiting new states,
for taking new actions.
And similarly, like
posterior sampling,
you can try to figure out
models of different dynamics
and so forth and
act accordingly.
But at the end of the day, when
you're in a very large MDP,
exploration from scratch
is generally intractable.
So for example, if you randomly
initialize a transformer
language model and
try to figure out
how to make a user happy, or
some other reward function,
like upvotes or
something like that,
actually, just using
upvotes to train a language
model from scratch
isn't going to work.
The sheer vastness of the
possible space of tokens
is way too large, at least
relative to the patients
that most users will have.
Likewise, in robotics,
if you're trying
to even just learn how to--
I don't know-- pour water
from one cup to another cup,
you're going to be stuck in a
realm where you're just randomly
moving arms around,
rather than actually
doing things that are useful
if you're starting completely
from scratch.
Instead, generally,
what exploration
looks like in these larger
domains is to rely heavily
on demonstrations, or on base
models that were pre-trained
on data and demonstrations.
So for example,
reinforcement learning
has been quite successful
in language models,
because, and
particularly in scenarios
where you have a strong
base model that already
knows how to write
coherent sentences,
and already knows
roughly how to approach
certain kinds of prompts, or
certain kinds of problems.
And likewise, in robotics,
if you have demonstrations
of example behavior that
achieve high reward,
then using that as a starting
point for reinforcement learning
is very powerful.
And generally, these models
are providing an initialization
that's really excellent
for exploration
and seeking out
potential things.
Wherever feasible,
it's also quite useful
to use shaped
rewards, because that
can guide any sort of
exploration process, as well.
And this could be if
you're in simulations.
You can hand code
sparse, dense rewards,
or if you're learning
single-step rewards
from preferences, that
actually also provides
a fairly dense reward signal.
This isn't to say you could
also combine some of these ideas
with demonstrations
and base models.
But generally, you
get a lot further
from starting with this
kind of initialization.
That said, there is still
potentially an exploration
problem that we started
to talk about last time.
And I want to revisit that,
now that we've actually
started to learn about
exploration in standard MDPs.
Yeah, exactly.
So the idea here is that if
you're in these kinds of MDPs,
the state space is enormous, and
all of the possible actions you
can take is enormous, as well.
And this is a way
to bias the model
towards a part of
the state space
that is going to
get high reward.
Yeah, giving it bias of,
these are the kinds of things
I want you to do.
So in particular, what
I'd like to talk about is,
say you have some model
that has been trained,
and it can do a
variety of things.
But there's scenarios
where when you're actually
deploying that
policy, you actually,
even if you have a lot
of prior experience,
you might need to
explore at test time
because you might not have
all the information you
need to get high reward.
And so we talked about a
couple examples on Wednesday
where, for example, you might
need to find ingredients
in a kitchen.
And to do that, you
can't just start cooking.
You need to open
drawers, open cabinets,
and so forth to try to
seek out information.
And second, in language
models for reasoning,
you might need to explore
different strategies that
might lead to a
solution to a problem,
rather than simply trying to
start writing tokens that you
think might lead
to the solution.
Now, we talked about this
kind of meta-RL problem
where we're optimizing a policy
with history, or with memory.
And generally,
memory should allow
agents to be able to
explore and exploit,
because they're able to
try different actions,
and remember what
they did, and then use
that information about
where ingredients
are to then solve the problem.
But we talked about how
if we optimize exploration
and exploitation together
with an end-to-end objective,
this is hard.
Because we have
this chicken and egg
problem, where if we haven't
yet learned how to explore, then
we can't actually get
high rewards because we
haven't found the ingredients.
And likewise, if we don't yet
know how to solve the task,
then we get low reward for any
sort of exploration behavior.
So there's this
coupling problem.
And we also talked about
some alternative exploration
strategies that are
easier to optimize,
but can lead to
suboptimal performance.
And what I'd like
to talk about is,
there's actually a method that
can both get optimal exploration
and exploitation trade-off,
and also be efficient to train.
So it sort of gets the
best of both worlds.
And the idea for
this is actually
going to build upon this
last alternative exploration
strategy.
Let's write this right here.
So the idea here is
that you can try to--
for different environments
or different tasks,
you could try to fit a dynamics
model and a reward model,
and then try to explore
in ways that tell us
more information about our
model of the environment.
And this should incentivize
the agent or the policy
to actually seek out
additional information
to explore in a way
that's decoupled
from executing on the task.
And so if you do this and
you have different MDPs that
correspond to navigating
to different circles,
and then you try to incentivize
it to take trajectories that
lead to a better
model of reward,
and better model of
dynamics, you actually
get a trajectory
that looks something
like the purple trajectory,
where it's explicitly
trying to visit
states that allow
it to learn where the reward
function is going to be.
Now, this can learn efficient
exploration strategies,
but it has its
downsides and it can be
suboptimal in some scenarios.
For example, if
there's distractors,
like if there's pictures
on the wall, for example,
then it's going to be looking
at all the pictures on the wall
to learn a good model of
those different environments.
So we can build upon
this idea and try
to learn how to explore
without learning a model.
And in particular, instead
of trying to learn a dynamics
and reward model,
we could instead
try to be able to
predict what the task is.
So we're going to label each
task with a identifier mu.
This could be either like
a one-hot like an index,
or it could be a
language description,
or it could be some more
continuous description
of the task, like
continuous vector.
And then what we
could do is we could
try to explore in a way
that allows us to predict
what the task is at hand.
So for example,
we'll have our say
that we have two policies,
and exploration policy
and exploitation policy.
In practice you
could combine these,
but it's helpful to think
about them as separate.
So we'll have our exploration
strategy or exploration policy.
This is going to produce some
experience in a particular task.
And our goal is for it
to be able to explore,
to be able to discern
different tasks.
And so we could
separately train a model
that's going to be
predicting the task
identifier from the experience
that we've collected so far.
And if we do
something like this,
then this sort of
exploration objective
is completely separate from
actually executing on the task.
The goal here is to be able to
predict the task identifier.
And then separate
from this, we could
train a policy that's trying
to execute on the task,
just using the
identifier for the task.
And this is just
multi-task learning
or multi-task
reinforcement learning,
and this we can train just
with optimizing reward.
And it doesn't rely on
having good exploration.
So here, we're able to decouple
the objective for execution
so it doesn't rely
on exploration,
and have an exploration
objective just based
on identifying the task that
isn't dependent on how well you
do the task.
So on the slides, we'll train a
policy in a task identification
model so that we collect data
that allows for accurate task
prediction.
And then we'll
also train a policy
that's conditioned
on the task ID,
in order to maximize
reward for each task.
So which part of this
is the exploration?
Is it the model that
predicts the identifier?
So the exploration is really
this policy right here.
And this model is
actually just going
to be used for the
reward for this.
And so we're going to be--
the reward for this
policy will be, basically,
how well this model is
identifying the task,
or basically, the negative error
of this task identifier model.
Good question.
The question is,
does this generalize
to new unseen task categories?
This can actually struggle
with generalization,
and we'll talk about that.
Let's go through meta-testing,
and then we'll talk about that.
So this is roughly
how training works.
And then at test time
if you've trained
all of these different
things, then you
can take your
exploration policy,
run it to collect experience,
then feed that experience
into your task identifier
model to get a task ID,
and then take that task
ID, and feed that as input
to your execution policy
to then execute the task.
So you'll then explore and
then identify the task,
and then exploit.
Now, getting back to that
question, the upside of this
is you don't need to
model dynamics or rewards.
You're just learning
this model that's
predicting the task identifier.
But if the task
identifier is just
a one-hot vector, for
example, this probably
isn't going to generalize
to new tasks very well.
And we'll see a solution
to that on the next slide.
The question is, what
is the main difference
from black box meta-RL that
we talked about before?
So we are still
sampling different MDPs.
The main difference is
simply the objective
for the exploration part.
So well, I guess there's
two main differences.
One is the objective or
the exploration part,
and then the second
is that here we're
going to be maximizing rewards,
similar to black box meta-RL.
But we're actually going to be
giving it this task identifier
so that it doesn't need
to rely on exploration,
or a good exploration
strategy when trying
to learn how to do the task.
Now we have this
generalization problem,
and we actually also have
a way to address this.
So instead of using this
task identifier directly,
we can actually try to learn a
more compressed representation
of the task that will
generalize more effectively
than a one-hot vector.
So as an example, when we
learn the execution policy,
we're also going to
identify information that's
needed for solving the task.
And so say that our
identifier consists
of a few things
that are relevant
and a few things that
are not relevant.
So it contains things
like wall color
and decorations,
but then it also
contains information about
where the ingredients are.
Then we'd like to
use-- and similar
if you had a one-hot
vector, it would also
contain information that
might be irrelevant,
because you might have two
Kitchens that have ingredients
in the same place, but then have
other things that are spurious.
And we'll try to then
bottleneck this representation
to compress away
the stuff that's not
needed for solving the task.
And if we can do this, then
this sort of representation
should generalize better.
And then when we
learn to explore,
instead of learning
to explore to be
able to predict the
identifier here,
we'll learn to
explore so that we
can recover this compressed
task representation.
And so try to be able to
explore so that you're
able to predict what this z
representation for the task is.
Now, how do you actually
compress representations
in neural networks?
So before we go into the
details of this algorithm,
let's talk about
that a little bit.
So we have our task
identifier mu, mu i,
and then we'd like to
have a neural network that
uses that to predict zi.
And then, we'll
then have a policy
that takes this and the
state and outputs the action.
And if we train this whole
thing end to end, it may not--
it's not necessarily
incentivized
to actually compress
information here,
to actually remove information
about decorations, for example.
So one thing we could do is
we could simply add noise
to this representation.
And so if you take
this, and instead
of feeding it directly here,
you could take this output zi.
And then right here, you could
basically add some noise.
So right here, what
you're doing is
you're adding some noise
where the noise is sampled
from a Gaussian distribution.
And if you add noise, then this
is going to discard information,
because you're adding--
you're kind of
corrupting the signal.
But you might discard
some good information,
especially if you do
this only at test time.
Now in principle,
you could also train
with this noise to encourage it
to discard information from z.
But if you train the policy
with this noise as input,
then what it could just
do is it could just
increase the
magnitude of zi here,
so that the magnitude
of the noise
is a lot smaller in comparison.
And so if you just
add noise, the model
can compensate and still
pass a lot of information
through this task
representation.
So that's not a great
solution, but what we can do
is we can just also
prevent the model
from increasing the magnitude.
And we can just
add a loss that--
we can modify our training
loss for the policy
to include a term that's going
to minimize the magnitude of z.
And if you do
this, you're then--
now if it kind of blows
up the magnitude of z,
then it will have
a high loss here.
And so it will be forced
to keep that magnitude down
to be lower, so that it is
actually forced to remove
information that isn't needed.
And any sort of magnitude
it does introduce,
it will be incentivized to only
have information that's needed
for predicting the action.
This is called a variational
information bottleneck, which
is a fancy term for saying
that you're adding noise,
and then also
modifying your loss
term to have this L2 penalty
on your representation.
One of the reasons why this is
called a variational information
bottleneck is that this
objective is actually
equivalent to minimizing the
KL divergence between your--
If you think about
this as a distribution,
because this is now kind
of a Gaussian distribution
with a mean of zi and
a variance according
to the variance
of epsilon, that's
equivalent to minimizing
the KL divergence
between that distribution and
the unit Gaussian distribution.
Yeah, so the question
is, why are we
creating a representation
of a one-hot vector?
So if we go back
to the algorithm
we talked about
before, where we are
exploring to
generate experience,
then trying to identify
the task, and then
condition on that task, if
we then want to quickly solve
a new task, then we'll be able
to use our policy to explore.
But then after we explore,
if our representation is
a one-hot vector here,
if it's a new task,
then that new task
may not cleanly
fit within one of the
previous one-hot vectors.
And so we'd like to have a
more continuous space that's
more compactly
representing the task,
and essentially learn this
latent task representation that
will generalize to new tasks.
Yeah, so the
question is, don't we
need more information
about the task,
whether or not two tasks
are related to each other?
Though, I guess the--
so when you think
about a one-hot,
it doesn't really seem like it
is necessarily capturing that
much information, but a
one-hot vector is actually less
compressed than
something that is--
something that's a
more continuous or less
discrete representation.
So say, for example, let's see.
Let's say, for example, that
one of your tasks is to go here.
This is task one.
Task two is to go here.
Task three is to go here,
and task four is to go here.
Then task one and task
four are very similar,
but when you use one-hot
vectors to represent them,
they are kind of represented
completely separately.
And if you try to learn a
task representation that's
compressing these,
then it will actually
learn a representation that puts
these much closer to each other.
The question is, do you need
to add epsilon to the loss?
So it doesn't end up
coming into the loss,
but you do need to add
it when you're actually
training the neural network.
So you're adding the noise
and you sample the noise
every-- resample the
noise every single time.
And the epsilon is sampled
from this distribution,
and you can think
about this distribution
as coming into the loss.
But yeah, you don't need to add
epsilon anywhere into the loss.
It just comes out to this.
So let's walk through, actually,
what this algorithm looks
like more completely.
So first, let's talk about
just executing on the task
separate from exploration.
So our goal is to learn this
task representation, this latent
task representation, and
how to solve the task.
And to do this,
we're going to have--
we have our task identifier.
And we're going to have a
network that produces zi.
We're going to add noise
to get zi plus epsilon.
And then we're going to pass
this and the state into our--
this is our execution
policy that's
going to produce an action.
And we can think about
this as having two parts,
so we have the execution
policy right here
that takes as input the
noisy zi and the state
to produce the action.
And then we also have
this part right here.
And we'll write this as some
encoder F that maps from mu
i to zi.
We can write this
as a distribution,
because if you fold this noise
into a distribution like this,
this will be some
distribution that is--
let's now call this z bar.
This is a distribution that
is a Gaussian with mean
of z bar i and some variance.
Let's just write it as
variance, like that.
So these are the two things
that have parameters, F and pi.
And we're going to train
both of these neural networks
to maximize reward,
so that we're actually
learning a representation,
such that we can solve the task
and predict actions
that maximize reward.
And then we're also going to
add the regularization on z.
And so our objective
here will be
maximizing the sum
of expected rewards
under our execution policy.
And since we're
maximizing here, we're
also going to be minimizing
this term right here, which
is equivalent to
the KL divergence.
So we'll be maximizing
the negative KL
divergence between
F of zi, given mu i,
and this unit Gaussian.
So on the slides,
there's the objective.
And this is just trying
to solve the task,
and also learn a latent task
representation based off
of the task ID.
It's going to be a vector,
so z is going to be a vector.
And so this should be an i.
But yeah, it'll be a vector.
And yeah, yeah.
So the question is, why are
we adding this information
bottleneck or this
KL divergence?
The reason is that we
want to learn a nice task
representation that's
throwing away information.
And if we don't add that
term, then this z right here,
this representation of
the task might still
contain a lot of
information that
are irrelevant for
actually solving the task.
And so it might contain--
if, for example, you
have two tasks that
have the ingredients in
the same exact place,
but something has changed about
the environment, like the wall
color is different, or different
objects in different places,
but those are irrelevant
to solving the task,
then z will include those
things that are irrelevant.
And then when you go
to explore, you're
then going to be
exploring things that
are irrelevant to the task.
Yeah, so the question
is, we are given
the task ID during training.
We actually don't
need it at test time.
So what does this look like
to generalize to new tasks?
When you are faced
with a new task,
you're going to use
your exploration policy
to explore and then predict a--
instead of predicting
mu i, you're
actually going to predicting zi,
your latent task representation,
and then feeding that
into your execution policy
to then execute or
exploit on the task.
The question is, can you
train the execution policy
to attend to the relevant parts?
So if you have a really good
task representation that doesn't
have irrelevant parts of the--
irrelevant things in it,
then you can skip this step
and basically zero out
those parts of the task
representation.
This would be in scenarios where
you don't have a one-hot vector,
but you already know
maybe one task--
Maybe if you have language
strings, for example,
and one task is turn left,
one task is turn right.
Another task maybe is
the same as turn left.
It's like you have the
task string for it.
It's basically the
same exact task.
Another task is to move forward.
If these are your different
tasks, you can get away with--
this is probably already a
very compact representation
because it's telling
you, are you turning?
Are you moving?
And so it's already telling
you about the relationship
between different tasks.
And so if your
task representation
is telling you about those
relationships, then--
or, for example, if you have
task representation that's,
like, the coordinates of
where you're trying to go,
then you're going to
have a task ID that's
very similar between
these two tasks.
And that will already
be quite compressed.
In those cases, you
can skip this step,
because those
representations will already
exclude irrelevant information.
But then if you instead have
a task ID that says one-hot
or that isn't very
informative, then you
need to compress that out.
And otherwise, there isn't--
this is one of the better
mathematical frameworks for
encouraging it to attend
to the relevant parts.
Yeah.
I guess in principle,
if you had a way
to change the way that this is
making decisions based on UI,
you might also be
able to do that.
Yeah, so what's the advantage
of outputting a distribution?
So the distribution here is
what allows us to compress.
And so by adding noise, or by
making this a stochastic neural
network, we're able to
remove information from it.
Whereas if you are
outputting-- if you're
passing a continuous
vector through,
there are heuristic
ways to try to compress,
for example, like by
compressing the dimensionality.
But you can still pass
infinite information
through even a one dimensional
continuous variable.
And so this is one way
that can, even in theory,
reduce information.
So now let's talk
about exploration.
So our goal in exploration is
to be able to try to predict z.
And I don't know
what notation I used.
So our goal is to try
to be able to collect
data that's predictive of z.
In practice, by the way, you
can train both of these policies
at the same time.
And we need to think about
how we would formulate
a reward function
that encourages
it to be predictive of z.
I don't know if--
I'll just pick some notation.
So say that we have--
we're going to be
learning some model that's
trying to be able to
predict z from the data
that we've collected.
And if we have some exploration
policy that's been exploring,
then we need to figure out
how to reward it accordingly.
And one thing that you could do
is you could collect some data,
and then at the end
of a trajectory,
for example, see how well
you can predict z and then
have the reward be the negative
prediction error for z.
and then zero everywhere else.
But if we did that, we'd
have a very sparse reward.
We'd only have it at the
end of the trajectory.
And what we can do is we
could actually incrementally,
at each time step, look
at how much information
we're gaining about z.
And that's going to give
us a more dense reward.
And so specifically, when we're
trying to train our exploration
policy, pi exploration, you can
think about the reward for St
At.
We could have it be the negative
prediction error times step t.
And that would be something
that's fairly reasonable.
But the action, like this
particular time step,
at this time step, we're
actually gaining just one time
step worth of information.
And if we wanted to
quantify that information,
we could actually look at
what was our prediction
error at the previous
time step, and look
at the relative difference in
the era of the previous time
step versus the error at
the current time step.
And that's how
much information we
gained from taking this action.
And so we could
define the reward
to be the prediction
error at t minus 1,
minus the prediction
error at time t.
And so how much?
This is something that should
be decreasing over time.
And this is basically
how better are we
at predicting zi
at the current time
step relative to the previous
time step, where prediction
error is something like--
is z hat minus the true zi.
And so we're
training this model.
We want this to be per
step information gain.
And so if we look
at all of the states
up until the current time
step versus all the time steps
up to the previous time step,
we can measure this notion
of information gain.
I guess maybe also to make
this a little bit more
clear, if this is
prediction error at time t,
then this means that z hat is
the estimate from Predicting z
from the data up until time t.
So everything in the
trajectory up until time t.
Cool.
So like many
research algorithms,
this has a somewhat
mangled, forced acronym.
So decoupled reward free
exploration and execution
in meta-RL, or DREAM.
And you'll be implementing this
algorithm in homework four.
So we talked before about
how if you train end-to-end,
if you train meta-RL
methods end-to-end,
and you're trying to
optimize for both exploration
and execution, you have
this coupling problem.
And the benefit is that you
can get optimal exploration.
And the downside is that
you're very, very inefficient.
And you can show
that this algorithm,
under fairly mild
assumptions, will actually
recover optimal exploration
and exploitation.
And then if you look at
the efficiency, which
is where end-to-end
optimization struggled,
you can think about it.
You can construct a simple
bandit problem, where--
a bandit-like problem, where
you have these different arms.
And arm zero, instead of
being a typical action,
is going to tell you what
is the optimal action.
And so if you, for
example, learn the strategy
of taking action zero, and
then taking the optimal action,
then that's like optimally
exploring and then exploiting.
And in an end-to-end
optimization,
you can actually quantify
how many samples it needs
for the meta learning process.
You get something
like A squared log
A, where A is the number of
arms or the number of actions,
whereas the DREAM algorithm
requires only A log A. There's
some assumptions here in
terms of using Q-learning,
using uniform exploration in
the outer loop of the algorithm.
And you can look at,
basically, the efficiency,
like how efficient
is the algorithm.
You can see that
DREAM is able to get--
is able to reach the optimal
behavior in many, many fewer
samples than if you were to use
end-to-end optimization, which
is shown in orange as a
function of the number of arms.
So as the problem gets
more and more complicated,
DREAM is able to
do far, far better
than end-to-end optimization.
We can also empirically
look at things.
So here's an example of
a meta-RL problem where
different tasks correspond
to going to different objects
with different colors.
And the color of the object
is written on the wall.
And so and the agent
starts over here
and it needs to walk around
the wall, walk around the wall,
read the color, and then
go to the correct object.
So it's exploring and then--
or seeking information,
and then exploiting.
It gets pixel rewards.
And if you compare end-to-end
algorithms that are shown here,
they really, really struggle
to do this end-to-end learning
to explore problem.
If you use one of the
alternative strategies
that we talked
about on Wednesday,
you can do better, in theory.
But you still have a suboptimal
exploration strategy.
Whereas with this
algorithm, you're
able to actually learn how
to explore, go find the sign,
and then go to
the correct object
by actually trying to
decouple exploration
for identifying the task,
and exploitation of solving
the task.
Cool.
And then you can
actually see this.
So here's a video of
the exploration episode
where it's walking
around and going
to read the sign on the wall
in this simple environment.
And then after it
reads the sign,
it's able to go to the blue key.
Yeah, that's a great question.
So the question is,
this is a setting where
exploration and exploitation,
you can first explore and then
exploit.
You might also have
tasks where you
need to interleave
exploration and exploitation,
where you first need to
find some information,
then use that to
accomplish a subtask
and then find an
exploration again.
We have done some work
that tries to combine them.
And you can, for example,
train a single policy
that uses the reward to identify
the task combined with the task
reward.
And if you're interested, I can
point you to a relevant work
there.
So to summarize
learning to explore
and learning policies
that know how to explore,
end-to-end can learn optimal
exploration and exploitation.
But if exploration is hard,
it's pretty hard to optimize.
And we saw an example of
that, where all of the methods
were kind of flatlining and
not learning good exploration.
Alternative strategies
are easier to optimize
and can be principled,
but can also
be suboptimal by large
amounts, and be very
inefficient about exploration.
And this decoupled approach
leads to the optimal strategy,
is also easy to optimize.
So it sort of gets the
best of both worlds.
It does require this
task identifier.
You need to at least be
able to enumerate your tasks
and know which of
those tasks you're in.
And that's the key thing
that it's using in order
to get the benefits.
Cool.
We have a little bit of time,
and so you could actually--
I wanted to briefly talk
about one application.
So you can take this
algorithm and use it
in a domain that's a little
bit different from what
we've seen before.
And this domain is trying to
find bugs in different computer
programs, and in particular, in
intro computer science courses,
although this would probably
apply to other programs,
as well.
It's really cool
for students to be
able to make computer programs.
It's very rewarding for
them to write a program
as they're learning how to code.
Then that creates a
program like this.
So on code.org, students
code up this game
called Bounce that looks a bit
like Pong, or one side of Pong,
where the goal is to hit
a ball into the goal.
In CS106A at Stanford,
students code up Breakout,
and so they might code
up a program like this.
This is an example of a buggy
game, where the ball actually
kind of gets skewered
by the paddle.
It kind of bounces
off the paddle,
rather than going and losing
a point or losing a life.
And we can basically treat
different student programs
as different tasks, where our
goal is to explore and find
the bugs that might exist.
And our ultimate
goal is to then be
able to provide feedback to the
student on the different bugs
in their program.
One of the other
things about this
is it's really time
consuming for TAs
or instructors to actually
grade and give feedback
on these assignments,
because you often
end up playing the game in order
to figure out and find the bugs.
Cool.
So we can use meta-RL.
We can actually use
exactly the DREAM algorithm
and train it to be
able to identify
different distinguishing
factors from different students.
And it can learn
exploration strategies,
like what happens if
the ball hits the goal.
So here, it's trying to actually
play the game successfully.
It can also check and
act, so what happens
if the ball hits the floor.
So it's actually purposely
trying to not hit the ball,
or also try to hit the
wall instead of the goal.
And this is an example
of a buggy program that
creates lots of different
balls as soon as the ball hits
the wall.
And then there was an
experiment in 106A two years ago
in the spring 2020 quarter,
where TAs actually used
the meta-RL algorithm in the
policy to basically grade
and pre-populate the
rubric for grading.
And then they just verified
that the rubric answers
were correct from watching the
videos of the meta-RL agent
playing the game.
And it led to 44% faster
grading, and also 6% more
accurate grading, and the
TAs generally liked using it.
They also used it
in at least one
subsequent quarter because
they liked using it so much.